# Ronan Sprake

19 Collingwood Close, Norwich, NR9 3QE 07944 277678 / ronansprake@gmail.com

# **Profile**

I'm an accomplished UX Designer with extensive in-house, agency and start-up experience. I design inclusive customer experiences with Agile and User Centred Design practices that deliver creative, sustainable solutions while remaining business focused and value driven.

My portfolio: https://ronansprake.co.uk/portfolio-rsprake.pdf

# **Key Skills & Attributes**

- Interaction design with a focus on usability, accessibility and information architecture (IA)
- Tools including Figma, Sketch, Adobe XD / CC, Axure, Invision, Proto, Zeplin, Jira and Trello
- Conducting user testing and research methodologies (qualitative and quantitative)
- Experience with a wide variety of web development, native apps and custom software
- A collaborative, pragmatic approach to design, strategic change and evolving requirements
- Encouraging transparency, trust and candid feedback to challenge my thinking
- Supportive and confident mentor for junior and mid-level designers

# **Employment History**

#### **Lead UX Designer - Upside Money**

March 2021 - Present

I joined an early stage startup to experience a Techstars Accelerator Programme. I lead the research and design of innovative products based on Open Banking technology, shaping the direction of our services.

- Executed the research and UX design of customer experiences across iOS and Web and B2B SaaS platforms, representing the voice of the customer at all stages
- Followed Lean UX practices to facilitate collaboration with distributed team members
- Established Design System foundations to introduce consistency and accessibility standards
- Uncovered and iteratively solved iOS onboarding issues, reducing failure demand
- Created a proposition testing framework, including surveys and interviews with B2B partners to understand pain points, analyse results and collate insights
- Built strong relationships with the engineering team, ensuring user stories are clearly understood and that design and development work hand-in-hand to achieve the best outcomes

### Senior UX Designer - Aviva

March 2017 - March 2021

I designed complex customer journeys across Aviva's digital estate including major parts of the Global Design System, enhancing experiences for over 31 million customers worldwide.

- Principal UX on Aviva's <u>Framework Design System</u>, used by 120 designers in 9 countries. I contributed designs while managing backlog for 2 UX designers, providing priorities and direction
- Produced journey maps, IA, sketches, wireframes and interactive prototypes for a variety of products, including quote & payment, car & home insurance, claims, investments and operations

- Estimated time and resource requirements for projects of all sizes
- Increased cross-discipline collaboration, leading to a ~50% increase in my team's sprint velocity
- Delivered actionable heuristic reviews for strategic partnerships (Barclays, HSBC and Santander)
- Interviewed and mentored designers, I also gave talks to groups of college and university students
- Presented Accessibility Champions Group sessions, promoting WCAG standards across Digital
- Gave skill-share presentations at monthly design meetings in Hoxton (80 UX/UI designers)

#### **UX Manager - Soak (digital agency)**

Jul 2015 - Mar 2017

Realising my strength and passion was for UX design, I worked with global brands including Red Bull, GE, The Economist and Games Workshop.

- Recruited, managed and mentored 2 UX designers and 2 UI developers
- Organised and led design workshops, lab and guerrilla testing
- Delivered successful design pitches (London, Paris, Salzburg)

#### **Lead UI Developer - Soak**

Jan 2012 - Jul 2015

Led creative product builds using Angular and React for clients including HSBC, IBM and Adnams.

UI Developer - Soak

Jan 2009 - Jan 2012

The first employee of a highly successful agency, I built design systems and emails for GE and Nissan.

### **Full Stack Developer - Digital Overload**

Nov 2007 - Jan 2009

A digital agency, I built digital products while training in Git, HTML, CSS, JS, PHP and MySQL.

#### IT Technician - Permastore

Oct 2005 - Nov 2007

Managed critical infrastructure, I also designed custom touchscreen and barcode interfaces.

# **Education**

Aviva	Aviva Certificate in General Insurance	2018
Open University	Certificate in Web Applications Development (Distinction)	2006 - 2008
University of Lancaster	History BA (Hons), (2:1)	2002 - 2005

## **Interests**

In the rare moments my young family isn't keeping me busy, I enjoy films (I've never seen Star Wars, please don't hold that against me) and I started baking during lockdown, with varying degrees of success.